====================
纪录片之家倾情奉献
http://www.jlpzj.net/
中字翻译：小开心  校对：hello @纪录片之家
本字幕仅供学习交流 严禁用于商业用途
==================================
多佛
Dover.
全欧洲最威胁的人
The most dangerous man in Europe
is about to arrive
即将在此登陆英伦
on Britain's shores.
他的福音煽动性十足
His preachings are so incendiary,
他被自己的祖国驱逐出境
he's been forced out
of his native country.
只有自由的英国向他敞开怀抱
Only liberal Britain will tolerate
his presence on her soil.
于是他在伦敦开始了流放生涯
He heads to London to live in exile.
那年是1849年
The year is 1849.
时至今日 他的著作仍具威胁性
But today, that man's writings
are still dangerous.
它是如此激进  如此具革命性
They're so radical,
so revolutionary,
世界仍被其一分为二
they continue to divide the world.
自他书写这个世界算起
It's been more than 150 years
已过去150年了
since he started writing
about the world.
但或许你不曾想到
But you know what?
若要审视全球的经济危机
If you're looking for an explanation
of the global economic crisis,
马克思是绝佳的出发点
he's a surprisingly good place
to start.
（他的追随者）把世界搞得一塌糊涂
你会想
With everything going so wrong,
you have to wonder,
卡尔・马克思的那套还能对到哪里去呢
is Karl Marx turning out
to be right?
大多数人知道马克思是共产主义的创始人
Most people know Marx
as the father of communism.
也许 对马克思对资本主义的绝大多数论述
You might be surprised to hear
that most of what he wrote
你会感到惊讶
was about capitalism.
但如今 全球商业核心圈都在认真思考
And today his ideas about that
are being taken seriously
他关于资本主义的观点
right at the heart
of global business.
他的理论正中要害
His analysis was pretty
on the button,
对我们目力所及的
and explains a lot, I think,
经济生活
about some of the things
that we see going on
马克思的理论很有意义
around in our economy today.
马克思对资本主义最大的批判是说
资本主义本质上就是不公平的
For Marx, the best argument against
capitalism was that it was
inherently unfair.
今天 他的观点
比以往任何时候更具共鸣
His ideas on inequality
have more resonance than ever today.
马克思就是要
What Marx did do
唤起我们的紧迫感
is to install this sense of urgency.
世界不能再这样继续下去了
Things cannot go on for ever
the way they are.
本系列 我将引领您回顾
以下三位杰出人物的
In this series, I'll tell you about
the lives and revolutionary thinking
生平及其革命性思想
of three extraordinary men...
约翰・梅纳德・凯恩斯
John Maynard Keynes,
弗里德里希・哈耶克
Friedrich Hayek,
和卡尔・马克思
and Karl Marx.
他们都身处激变的时代
Their worlds were changing
as never before.
他们都发现货币驱驰着国家
They saw that the fate of nations
would hang on the power of money
对于如何控制货币
and they had radically
different ideas
给出了各不相同的主张
about how to control it.
今天 赌注不可能再高了
Today, the stakes could
hardly be higher.
三位大师的思想流传至今
All three of these men were giants
whose ideas live on.
但此刻 人们记住的是
But they speak to us right now
because they, more than anyone,
正是他们认识到货币是一把双刃剑
recognised the double-edged
power of money...
市场在变革人们生活方式的同时
how markets could transform
all of our lives,
也使我们陷于混乱
but also plunge us into chaos.
凯恩斯和哈耶克
就政府是否应该对――资本主义
Keynes and Hayek argued about
whether government
――这一人类的本性
进行管制有所争辩
should try to tame this force
of human nature, capitalism.
卡尔・马克思则提出最为激进的方案
――消灭资本主义
Karl Marx had the most radical
advice of all - get rid of it.
货币大师   马克思
1989年  马克思名誉扫地
In 1989, Karl Marx's reputation
lay in ruins.
一片荒芜
What a mess!
对我们大多数人来说 柏林墙的倒下
For most of us, the fall
of the Berlin Wall
意味着马克思主义的终结
meant the end of Marx.
数百万人逃离警察国家
Millions rejected the horrors
不再有暴力镇压的恐怖
of a violent and repressive
police state.
由于曾被这些共产主义国家奉为圭臬
And because the Communist countries
claimed Marx as their inspiration,
人们对马克思主义也嗤之以鼻
his ideas were cast aside, as well.
柏林墙倒塌之际
When this wall came down, I was just
我正在大学学经济
studying economics at university.
那时 我们认为
Back then we knew,
至少我们自认为
or we thought we knew,
了解马克思及其共产主义的两个方面
two things about Marxism, Communism.
一是与其声称的相反  它没有给予工人以自由
One was it hadn't delivered freedom
for the workers. Quite the opposite.
第二条  对一个经济学家来说更糟
And the other, just as bad
if you're an economist,
那就是它没有带来繁荣
was it hadn't delivered prosperity.
共产主义的经济路数行不通
The Communist approach
to the economy just hadn't worked.
当西方的自由市场制度兴盛一时之际
While the free market West
took great strides,
共产主义的计划经济被弃之如敝屣
the Communist planned economies
had been left behind.
马克思作为经济学家的名声狼藉
Marx's reputation as an economist
was in shreds.
然而过去几年世道骤变
In the last few years,
something strange has happened.
似乎全球的金融危机
It's like the global
financial crisis
使马克思主义又死灰复燃
has brought Karl Marx
back from the dead.
虽然我们仍不接受他的共产主义
And we still don't care what he said
about Communism,
但人们开始回想起他对资本主义的批判
but people are going back to his
damming assessment of capitalism,
不禁怀疑他所说的――
资本主义其根深蒂固的顽疾
all its deep seated flaws,
with a nagging doubt.
今天是否真的发作了
Is it all now coming true?
世道昌明 没人会想起马克思
When times were good,
Marx was nowhere.
但如今 西方深陷经济危机
But now the western economies
are in crisis
他的理论又引起
he's attracting new interest
权威经济学家的关注
right at the heart
of the economic establishment.
国际货币基金组织的前首席经济学家：
From a former IMF chief economist...
从很多方面来说 马克思是对的
Marx is right
on a number of dimensions.
收入不均
He certainly is right
导致贫富阶层关系紧张  这一点没错
that income inequality can be a
source of tremendous tension.
预见到2008年经济危机的人：
To the man who saw
the 2008 crisis coming.
他认识到 资本主义
He had understood
that there are situations
以及全球经济一体化
in which capitalism
and globalisation
会引发经济危机
can lead to economic crisis.
世界知名银行的经济学家：
And an economist at one of the
world's leading banks.
要说服切尔西或切姆斯福德的人
It's quite hard to convince people
who live in Chelsea or Chelmsford
马克思主义跟他们很相关 这很难
that this is of great relevance
to them, but actually,
但现在值得一试
it's worth a bash.
切尔西和切姆斯福德的居民认为马克思
不过就是共产主义 但如今他们会惊讶的
Anyone in Chelsea or Chelmsford
who thinks Marx is only about
communism, is in for a shock.
马克思批判的资本主义如今正在此地上演
It's what he said about capitalism
that rings so true today.
马克思的关键洞见是
他看到资本主义本质上是不稳固的
Marx's key insight was that
capitalism was inherently unstable.
他说 经济危机会一直伴随我们
He said we'd lurch
from crisis to crisis
社会的不公将日益加大
and society would become
increasingly unequal.
马克思将世界分为资本家和工人两个阶级
Marx divided the world
into bosses and workers.
他认为 他们的争议难以调和
For him, they would always be
at odds
并将导致危机
and that battle
was a recipe for crises.
为了攫取利益 资本家榨取工人
To make profit, bosses squeeze
what they pay workers.
当工人们没有足够的钱
购买资本家售予他们的物品时
The crisis comes when workers
then don't have enough money
危机就爆发了
to buy what bosses
are trying to sell them.
二战后的几十年间
这套理论看似站不住脚
And for decades after World War II,
that looked completely wrong.
我们经济增长稳定
We had years of stable growth,
工人们在经济增长的蛋糕中
分享到越来越多的份额
and the workers were taking a
larger and larger share of the pie.
但现在不是了
But not anymore.
马克思解释了为什么会发生经济危机
他注意到
Marx would explain this crisis
in terms of the fact
普通人挣的钱不够花
that ordinary people haven't got
enough money to spend.
为什么没钱花
Why haven't they got enough
money to spend?
因为钱被重新分配了
Because there's been a big
redistribution,
过去几十年来都是这样
over the last few decades,
钱从普通人手里转移到资本家 富人手里
away from ordinary people
towards capital, towards wealth.
马克思认为 这一切不会改变
And for Marx,
there's no turning back.
他认为人类历史的发展犹如
牛顿运动定律那般
He thought there were laws of motion
running through human history.
资本主义的危机会越来越严重
Capitalism would produce
bigger and bigger crises
最终它将灭亡
and then it would collapse.
他认为迫使资本主义灭亡的这股力量
And he believed that the force
driving us to this final collapse
跟推动这个世界的动力是一样的
was the same one that built our
world in the first place...
那就是金钱的力量
the power of money.
对于危机 马克思有一个很简单的方程式
Marx had a very simple formulation
about crises,
显示资本主义的根本缺陷
which is that they are manifestations
of the fundamental flaws,
或者如他所说的资本主义难以调和的矛盾
or contradictions,
as he called them, of capitalism.
马克思的危机解决方案
How would Marx have suggested
solving the crisis is,
当然就是消除资本主义
of course, by abolishing capitalism.
资本主义是否超过自己的大限了呢
Is capitalism living on borrowed time?
有时 这也没什么难理解的
Sometimes it doesn't feel
that farfetched.
来到这儿 让人的思绪萦绕于马克思
Here's why I've been thinking
more about Marx...
因为过去几年的经济衰退很不寻常
it's cos the last few years hasn't
felt like an ordinary recession.
它不是西方某个经济体
It hasn't felt like a crisis
for one economy
或是一组经济体遭受危机
or for a group of economies
in the West.
而是整个体系 即所谓的资本主义制度
At times it really has felt like
a crisis for the system,
遭受危机
for capitalism as we know it.
所以 你得着眼一个更宽泛的解释
You want a bigger explanation.
从这个意义上讲  没人比马克思
And no-one's ever had
a bigger explanation
给出的解释更深刻了
for everything that's happened
than Karl Marx.
对资本主义最严厉的批判家
Capitalism's most implacable critic
诞生在风景如画的小镇特里尔
was born in the picture-postcard
town of Trier,
现位于德国西南部
in what is now southwest Germany.
如今 他的出生地为本地经济贡献良多
Today, his birthplace makes its own
contribution to the local economy...
这儿吸引了大量游客
it's a big draw for tourists.
有很多游客 来自世界各地
But do you still have a lot of
people coming here, tourists,
慕名而来吧
from around the world?
是的 每年差不多有4000名游客
Yes, we have more than 40,000
tourists a year
其中四分之一来自中国
and 25% came from China.
四分之一来自中国  是的
So, a quarter of them come from
China... Yes, yeah.
来参观马克思的出生地  是的
To see Marx' birthplace. Yeah.
他们买些什么纪念品吗 他们喜欢什么
And what do they buy,
what do they like?
他们喜欢红巧克力
They like the red chocolate.
卡尔・马克思巧克力
The Karl Marx chocolate.
也许 我也应该带上些
Maybe I should get some of that,
as well, actually.
还有酒
And the wine.
马克思的父亲 海因里希・马克思
在特雷尔附近有一座葡萄园
Well, Marx's father, Heinrich Marx,
he had a vineyard nearby Trier.
您认为 马克思不会介意
你们售卖这些东西吧
And you don't think that Karl Marx
would mind you selling all this stuff?
开这个店 有点资本主义啊
A bit capitalist, having this shop.
也许他会喜欢的吧  他是个很有幽默感的人
Perhaps he'd enjoy it
because he had a good humour too.
这个把我们的世界纳于其宏大理论的人
The man with the big theory
about our world
一开始就显露出凌云之志
had big dreams right from the start.
17岁时
When he was 17,
马克思要写一个未来的职业计划
Marx had to write an essay about
picking the right career.
他说此生要为全人类服务
He said the best position in life
was to serve all of mankind,
“你的事业会获得永生
so your deed would live on
perpetually at work
面对你的骨灰 高尚的人将洒下热泪”
and over your ashes would be shed
the hot tears of noble people.
我怀疑 这个了不起的年轻人
I wonder, would that young man,
that rather grand young man,
是否对自己的故居被建成博物馆而惊讶呢
be surprised to hear that his first
home had been turned into a museum?
也许不会吧
Probably not.
虽说抱负远大 但马克思可不是个好学生
But for all his ambitions,
Marx was hardly a model student.
在柏林上大学时
When he was at university in Berlin
他即获得激进分子的名号
he earned a reputation
as a radical thinker.
马克思可以说是一个
Marx comes across as a young man,
as this, sort of,
精力充沛 有血性的危险人物
energetic, fiery, hairy figure.
他被称为是“沼泽里的野猪”
He was known as the
Wild Boar of the Moor,
这被用来形容他早年复杂的性格
which, sort of, points to his,
sort of, Levantine complex.
他主意超多 超爱争辩
He was full of ideas.
He was full of debate.
他爱推杯换盏 之后进行思辨的争论
He liked big drinking sessions
and then deep philosophical debate
话题是 基督的本质啦
德国的浪漫主义 以及政治等
about the nature of Christ
and German Romanticism and politics.
24岁时
By the time he was 24,
我们的马克思博士颇有文艺复兴的范儿
Dr Marx was a bit
of a renaissance man.
可以说是法律 哲学方面的专家
He was an expert in law,
philosophy, you name it.
事实上 当时他不太懂的就是经济
In fact, the only thing he didn't
know much about was economics.
但1842年之后 一切都变了
That all changed in 1842.
那时 马克思是一家报社的编辑
Marx, by now working as a journalist,
他听闻了一个有关林地的争论
heard about a controversy in this wood
这场争论帮助马克思
that would help shape his understanding
定型了其世界观
of how the world works.
农民从这片林子中捡拾柴火
Peasants taking sticks from the
forest floor to use as firewood
但他们却被人控告犯有偷盗罪
were being prosecuted for theft.
几世纪来 这片林地一成未变
Wood had been gathered here
for centuries
但突然 地主说这片地归他们了
but now the landowners had declared
it belonged to them.
原本自由拾取的柴火现在成了私有财产
What had been freely shared
was now private property.
可以说 正是从这件事开始
You could say
that thinking about this question
让马克思变身为一个经济学家
turned Marx into an economist,
但这只是个起点
but that wouldn't really capture it.
马克思开始思考经济问题
He came to think that economics,
他认为人与人之间的经济关系
the nature of economic relationships
between people,
是所有关系中最核心的
were at the heart
of absolutely everything.
马克思主义的理论基础是唯物主义
The foundations of Marx's thinking
was materialism,
即抽象掉宗教 意识形态 政治因素
that when you cut away religion,
ideology, politics,
最后只剩人与人之间的
at its root were the material relations
物质关系――衣食住行等
between man - the need for food,
基本的生活需求
the need to have a roof over your head.
这便是人际互动中的终极驱动力
This is what ultimately drives
so much of human interaction.
马克思独特的地方在于
经济在他看来
What was unique in Marx,
he didn't see economy
不仅仅是一个特殊领域
just as a special sphere.
他把它视作整个社会关系中
He saw economy as
the structuring principle
最根本的一项
of the entire social totality.
马克思认为 一切都源自私有财产
For Marx, it all begins
with private property,
正是它赤裸裸地把世界区分为...
which divides the world starkly...
有产者
there are those that have it,
跟无产者
and those that don't.
拿这些木头来说
Take this wood.
它成为私有财产前 我可以随心所欲地处置
Before it became private property,
I could do what I liked with it.
拿它当柴火给房子供暖或者做把椅子
I could heat my house with it,
I could make a chair
或者拿它去换食物
and exchange it for food.
但它若成为某人的私有财产
整个关系就变了
But if it belongs to someone else,
the whole relationship changes.
按照马克思的说法 我就成了无产者
Now Marx would say I've become
a member of the proletariat,
必须为这片林地的主人
now I have to work
for the owner of the wood,
也就是资产阶级工作 以换取工资
the capitalist, for a wage.
然后他才会把我的劳动产品卖给我
Then he can sell what I've made
而价格却比我的工资还高
for more than he paid me.
瞧 都发生了什么
Look what's happened,
我生活中的某些部分 财产上发生了转移
something that was part of my life
is now a financial transaction.
资本家赚取了利润
And the capitalists made profit.
这些利润 他可以拿去买更多木头 开工厂
He can use that to buy more wood,
build factories,
以赚取更多利润
make more profit.
这样周而复始 利润成为全部的动力
And so it goes on. Profit
is now the heart of everything.
这就是马克思主义的资本主义理论
So, there you have it -
the Marxian view of capitalism,
或是其精髓吧
or the gist of it, anyway.
如果你想了解更多 那就得去啃
If you want more,
you'll have to wade through
马克思的皇皇巨著了
hundreds of pages of Marx, yourself.
我们所关心的是资本主义的源动力
The key point for us is that
that driving force of capitalism,
即源源不断地攫取利润
the need to earn more
and more profit,
马克思认为 这也将引发不断的危机
well, Marx thought that was also
a recipe for constant crises.
马克思会说
So, Marx would say
追溯现在这场经济危机
you could trace the roots
of the crisis we're in today
其根源都是资本主义的本质
right to the very heart of capitalism,
即追求利润
to its need to generate profit.
马克思在特雷尔就预见到
这个变动不居的世界
What Marx was seeing in Trier
was a world in flux.
封建主义正步出历史舞台
Feudalism was on the way out...
一种全新的生产方式来临
an entirely new way of doing things
had arrived.
如今 我们对资本主义了如指掌
Now, we know what capitalism's
really made of,
今天 金钱的力量
and the power of money today
远比把几个农民送进监狱更强大
means a lot more than just
throwing a few peasants in jail.
交易所里的几号人
A bunch of guys on a trading floor
可以把世界经济玩个底朝天
can turn the entire economy
upside down.
世界范围内 我们的生活都依赖于市场
Around the world, all of our lives
depend on markets,
依赖于资本主义制度下的物流
on capitalism being able to deliver.
如果马克思是对的
资本主义有其天生的缺陷
If Marx is right,
if it's fundamentally flawed,
那问题就严重了
well, that's a really big problem.
现代经济是个错综复杂的混合体
We might see a complex, modern economy,
我们谁也无法置身其外
which all of us have a stake in.
马克思主义者会说  老的那套依旧适用
But Marxists would say
the same old rules still apply.
他们认为 有产者仍掌控一切
For them, who owns what
still means everything.
工人仍辛苦劳碌
They see workers still slaving away
资产阶级或是布尔乔亚们
and capitalists, or bourgeoisie,
仍在剥削工人
still exploiting them,
以攫取更多利润
always striving to make more profit.
马克思认为 任何不追求利益最大化的资本家
In Marx's world, any capitalist
that doesn't seek maximum profit
将很快被别人取代
is soon replaced by one who does.
所以 整个体系的过程完全可以预见
So, the system follows a completely
predictable course,
那就是趋向崩溃
he would say,to its own destruction.
对此 很多人并不接受
It's not an idea
that many people accept.
他大错特错
He was completely wrong,
说什么资本主义只是一个过渡阶段
including the idea that capitalism
was merely a phase,
自身就包含了毁灭的种子
and contained within it the seeds of
its own destruction.
完全不是那回事
That's not the case.
任何事物 放眼足够长的时间都会灭亡
Well, everything is bound to
collapse if you wait long enough.
地球也逃不脱
I mean, the earth's going to,you know,
某天被太阳吞没的命运
sucked into the sun, some day.
资本主义的完全灭亡 这听起来难以置信
You'd be forgiven for thinking
the total collapse of capitalism
但却情有可原
sounds a little implausible.
追求利润怎么就是灾难呢
How could seeking profit
be so disastrous,
它不是也成就了诸多伟业吗
when it's done such amazing things?
看看资本主义制度下我们的口福
Just look at how
we eat under capitalism.
我们得享来自世界各地的水果
We get fresh fruit flown in
from all over the world.
光早餐就有700种谷类食品可供选择
We can choose from 700 types
of breakfast cereal.
应有尽有 而且绝对安全
We have enough of it
and it's all safe to eat.
充足的物资供应 令人难以置信
There's incredible plenty
而其依赖的技术并不局限于本国
and the technology it depends
on didn't come from the state.
这些都是资本家竞相逐利的结果
It's what happens when you let
capitalists compete for profit.
他们这么做不是为我们
They didn't do it for our benefit.
而是为自己致富
They did it because it made them rich.
所以 乍听起来
So, at first glance, Marx's idea
马克思说资本主义逐利的本质
会使其灭亡
that capitalism's search for profit
would be its downfall,
完全是无稽之谈
sounds absurd.
利润这词听起来有些贬义
Profit may often sound venal,
it may often sound wrong,
但它却有助于进步
but it is what pushes progress ahead.
可以说是利润推动了世界的发展
Profit is actually what drives
the world forward
这是马克思主义者不能否认的
and that's what Marx
could never quite handle.
逐利就是世界的本质
The profit motive is essential.
什么是趋利避害
I mean, after all,
what is the profit motive?
就是人们为了自己的利益奔忙
It's just a way of achieving
a better society
从而也营造更美好的社会
by people wanting to better
their own individual lot.
正是利益的驱动
When you think of how fundamentally
the profit motive
塑造并繁荣了我们的世界
has shaped and enriched our world,
怪不得马克思那套不受欢迎了
it's no wonder Marx
fell out of favour.
但据此完全摒弃马克思也不对
But you shouldn't dismiss
Dr Marx quite yet.
马克思的确过多关注阶级剥削 穷困
I mean, it's true he talked a lot
about class exploitation, misery,
混乱 但他并没有
把资本主义贬得一无是处
chaos, but he didn't think
capitalism was all bad.
远不是这样
Far from it.
伦敦Soho区的这间鸡尾酒吧
隐藏着一段革命史
This cocktail bar in London's Soho
hides a revolutionary past.
它过去是红狮酒吧
It used to be the Red Lion pub,
1847年 共产主义者曾在此秘密聚会
site of a clandestine
meeting of communists in 1847
那时 共产国际正风起云涌
that would echo down the ages.
正是这次会议 马克思和他的挚友
It was at that meeting
that they commissioned Karl Marx,
弗里德里希・恩格斯被委任
and his side kick Friedrich Engels,
to write
为有史以来最具煽动性的宣传册执笔
one of the most incendiary pamphlets
of all time,
《共产党宣言》
the Communist Manifesto.
有些你们或许知道
Some of this you probably know.
著名的开场白――
“一个幽灵在欧洲游荡”。
The famous opening line -
"A spectre is haunting Europe."
当然还有最后――
无产者在革命中失去的只是锁链。
And of course the end, about the
workers having nothing to lose but their chains.
他们获得的将是整个世界。
"They have a world to win.
以及大写的：全世界无产者联合起来
"Working men of all countries
UNITE!" in capital letters.
但你或许不知 我找到最有趣的
But what you probably don't know,
what I find most interesting,
是在中间
is what's in the middle.
这是我见过的 对资本主义
One of the most perceptive,
最有洞察力 最赞赏性的文字
and admiring, bits of writing
about capitalism I've ever read.
实际上 相比于成书之时
现在看来真实性更强
In fact, it reads a lot truer now
than when it was written.
我发现  令人惊讶的是
在马克思的诸多作品中
I think what's surprising
about a lot of Marx's writing
即便是有关共产主义的著作中
is that you find, in amongst
the communism,
对资本主义都有很多精妙的分析
a lot of good analysis of capitalism
and actually you also find within it
甚至是赞誉
quite a lot of praise
for capitalism.
马克思对资本主义的态度很暧昧
Marx's attitude towards capitalism
is basically ambiguous.
一方面 他很真诚
He's, at the same time,
he was honest, here, Marx,
对资本主义极度沉迷
ultra-fascinated.
He was fully aware
他深知 从人类历史看 资本主义
that this is the most productive,
dynamic system
是最有活力和生产力的制度
in the history of humanity,and so on.
马克思清楚  逐利的本性
The truth is, Marx did understand
that the drive for profit
会获得难以置信的物质增长
would achieve incredible things.
它第一个证明了
人的活动能够取得什么样的成就
"It has been the first to show
what man's activity can bring about.
它创造了完全不同于
"It's accomplished wonders
far surpassing
埃及金字塔 罗马水道
"Egyptian pyramids, Roman aqueducts
和哥特式教堂的奇迹
"and Gothic cathedrals.
它完成了完全不同于
"It has conducted expeditions
that put in the shade
民族大迁徙和十字军征讨的远征
"all former exoduses
of nations and crusades."
他预见到了全球化
He did really get
the kind of global aspect.
预见到了
He got the idea
突然间 人们得以从全球不同的地方
that people were suddenly being able
to get things
获取他们想要的东西
from all the way round the world
这是史无前例亦是冲击巨大的
in a completely new way
and the impact of that.
不断扩大产品销路的需要
The need of a constantly expanding
market for its products
驱使资产阶级奔走于全球各地
chases the bourgeoisie over
the whole surface of the globe.
它必须到处落户 到处开发
It must nestle everywhere,
settle everywhere,
到处建立联系
establish connections everywhere.
这全凭它自己的意志
It creates a world after its own image.
但资产阶级有其天生的缺陷
But you know, there's got to be
a downside for the bourgeoisie.
现代的资本主义社会恰似一个男巫
Modern bourgeois society
is like the sorcerer
他不再能支配
who is no longer able to control the
powers of the netherworld
自己用符咒呼唤出来的魔鬼
whom he has called up by his spells.
资本阶级生产的
What the bourgeoisie therefore
produces above all
不过是它自己的掘墓人
is its own gravediggers.
资产阶级的灭亡和无产阶级的胜利
Its fall, and the victory
of the proletariat,
是同样不可避免的
are equally inevitable.
听起来有点绕  但他的确提出了一个难题
It's stirring stuff,
but it does raise a bit of a puzzle.
为什么马克思认为资产阶级 布尔乔亚
How can Marx think the capitalists,
the bourgeoisie,
如此精彩但又注定失败呢
are so brilliant and yet so doomed?
在马克思看来  这都在于他们对待员工的方式
Well, for him, it all came down to
the way they treat their staff.
要理解马克思对资本主义危机的分析
To understand Marx's analysis of crises
我们首先得了解他对资本主义的解读
we have to first understand
the capitalism that he knew.
19世纪 资产阶级的确创造出
19th century capitalists
might have built wonders
超越了埃及金字塔那样的奇迹
surpassing Egyptian pyramids,
但代价是逼迫工人
but they also forced their workers
接受难以忍受的工作环境和工资
to endure terrible conditions and pay.
工业革命
The Industrial Revolution
及其后难以置信的成就
and all the incredible achievements
that followed
这些之所以能实现
离不开煤矿工人的贡献
were made possible by coal miners.
这儿再现了维多利亚时期矿井的原貌
This is a replica of what it were
like in Victorian era underground.
你能看到 远处有个人拿着镐和铁锹
The man you can see at far side
he had a pick and shovel,
他在挖煤 直到把煤筐装满
e would work the coal, fill that corf.
而他的妻子要把身后的煤拉到装卸点
And his wife had to drag the coal
behind her to a loading point
那大概有三四十米远吧
which, well, could be
up to 30 or 40 metres away.
我没料到 竟会是夫妻两人都在这儿工作
I didn't realise that they were
husband and wives that worked here.
哦 是的  都是一家人齐上阵
Oh, yeah, it were all families.
他们还要让一个小男孩或小女孩
They needed a little boy
or a little girl
在门口工作
to work this door as well.
所以 要做这份工作还得生个小孩
But if you took the job you had
to provide a small child, so...
是的 他们仅有的照明就是一根蜡烛
Yeah. The only light they had between
them were a candle
由父亲拿着 好看清采煤的工作面
which their dad kept so he could see
where he was in the coal face,
男孩或女孩呢
so the little boy or girl
就在黑暗中 孤零零地一天独坐12个小时
was sat on their own, in the dark,
for twelve hours a day.
对欧洲工业化时期的恐怖景象
It is difficult to overstate
怎么夸大都不为过
the horror of industrialisation
in Europe.
以1829年的利物浦为例
In 1829 Liverpool, for example,
平均寿命只有28岁
the life expectancy at birth
was about 28 years.
这是自黑死病后最低的数字
And that was the lowest age
since the Black Death.
所以 工业革命给人们的生活带来的冲击
So the impact of the Industrial
Revolution on life chances
绝对是十分可怕的
was absolutely terrifying.
至1849年 马克思因其煽动革命的著作
By 1849, his revolutionary
writings had got Marx
被各国驱逐 只有英国接纳了他
banned from everywhere but Britain.
在这里 他观察到金钱的力量
是怎么毁掉人的生活
Here he could observe the power
money had to ruin lives,
当然 在适当安全的距离之外
at a suitably safe distance, of course.
过去几分钟
I think in the last few minutes
我与维多利亚时代的苦役生活
有了亲密接触
I've come closer to what
it was actually like,
马克思都未曾做到过
the drudgery of Victorian times,
than Karl Marx ever did.
他可从未下过矿井 而且据我们所知
He never went to a mine
and as far as we can tell
直到他人生末期他才去过一家工厂
he only went to a factory once
towards the end of his life.
不过 这没能阻止马克思生动地呈现
But it didn't stop him
writing vividly
英国黑暗 罪恶 恐怖的矿井
about the horrors of Britain's dark,
satanic mills.
正是维多利亚时期工人们恶劣的工作环境
The horrors of Victorian
working conditions
造就了马克思的经济理论
clearly shaped Marx's economics.
在那个年代 工人的工资越低
意味着老板们的利润越高
In his time, minimum pay for proles
meant maximum profits for bosses,
谁要是工资开得高  等待他们的是破产
and any bosses who did choose
to pay more usually went bust.
他认为工资会越压越低
He thought there'd always be
downward pressure on wages
低到最后的工资
and that wages would come down to
the minimum
只能勉强能维持生计
that enabled bare survival.
工资不能再低了 否则工人没法活了
They couldn't go lower than that,
otherwise the workers would die.
但马克思认为工资会朝那个最低点逼近
But he thought they'd be
depressed down to that minimum.
但事实却恰恰相反
The reality, of course,
has been the opposite.
工资一直在增长
It has been a continual advancement
in wages, year in year out,
数十年都是那样
decade in decade in, decade out.
马克思错了
Marx was wrong.
他认为 形势会越来越糟
He thought it would all get so bad
工人最终会起来造反
the workers would overthrow the system.
然而 即便在他写作的年代
Yet even as he was writing,
已经有改革者开始着手去除
这套雇佣关系中最不利的方面
reformers were beginning to get rid
of the worst employment practices.
资本主义趋向温和  而非恶劣
Capitalism got kinder, not nastier.
但马克思的洞见  资本家追逐利润
But the idea that the competing
interests of bosses
工人们爆发危机
这些反倒适用于今天的情况了
and workers would cause crises,
well, that does seem relevant today.
马克思的理论很深奥
That's a very sophisticated argument,
让我用玩偶来解释一下吧
so, I'm going to need children's
toys to explain it.
首先 我要强调的是
But let me say, right at the start,
这些玩偶都不准备发起什么暴力革命
none of these toys endorse
any kind of violent revolution.
好 这个玩偶好比是矿主
Now here's a mine owner -
capitalist.
这是矿工 哦帽子掉了
Miners, with or without hat.
假设本来矿工不多
Now, imagine that there aren't very
many miners around.
矿主为了和其他资本家竞争工人
Then the mine owner has to compete
with the other capitalists
他将不得不开出较高的工资给工人
for workers, probably ends up having
to pay them more than he'd like to.
问题是 人工上去了
Trouble is, those higher costs
会削减利润
cut into profits.
如果整个经济体都是这种情况
Now if that's happening across
the economy,
利润率会逐渐下降
you've got a declining rate
of profit
很多资本家会破产
and a lot of capitalists
going out of business.
这就是危机了
You get a crisis.
无数工人将失业
You get countless workers
losing their jobs,
他们艰难度日 直到工资下降
having a terrible time,
until finally wages fall far enough,
资本家再次雇佣他们
the capitalists can go back
to exploiting them again.
所以 高工资对经济也不好
So, high labour
costs are bad for business.
但马克思认为
资本主义的崩溃之所以不可避免
But what makes the collapse
of capitalism inevitable for Marx
是因为哪怕资本家获得了其所需的资源
is that the bosses are in trouble
even when they have things
他们依旧麻烦缠身
their own way.
现在 假设形势反过来
Now, imagine the opposite situation.
有大批的工人 他们得竞争上岗
You've got loads of workers, all of
this lot competing for a single job.
无疑  老板们乐开花
Then, well, no wonder he's smiling,
他们只需要付给工人
the capitalist only has to pay
the workers
最低工资即可
the bare minimum.
这个桶 用马克思的话来说
This bucket is what Marx
would have called
就是失业人口构成的产业后备军
the industrial reserve army
of the unemployed.
只要那个桶是满的 竞争上岗
As long as that's full,
this lot can keep paying
就能维持低工资并创造丰厚利润
very low wages
and keep making profits.
除非最终引发大问题
Except, in the end,there's a problem.
因为低薪的工人没钱消费
Cos badly paid workers
don't spend very much,
而一个经济体中 消费不足对商业是不利的
and not very much spending in an
economy is not good for business.
这又会引发危机  更多的资本家破产
You get another crisis,
more capitalists going bust,
而这种危机更难愈合
and this crisis
is going to be harder to fix.
现在你知道为什么马克思认为
无论资产阶级怎么做
So, you can see why Marx thought
the capitalists were in trouble
他都会陷入困境了吧
no matter what they do.
他们从未想过要付给工人更多工资
They never want to pay
the workers more money.
他们一心只想逐利   但正是逐利的本性
They always need to make more
profit. But in seeking out profit,
最终会损毁他们赖以生存的基石
they end up eroding the basis on
which it's made.
可以这么说 他们忘了
They've forgotten, if you like,
他们的钱最终是从哪儿来的
where their money
ultimately comes from.
正如马克思的警句说的
The punch line, as ever with Marx,
资本主义注定灭亡
is that capitalism is doomed.
这就是工资是如何引发危机的
So, that's how problems with wages
can cause crises,
至少理论上是这样
at least in theory.
这套理论跟眼下的危机又有啥关系呢
But how is any of that
relevant to right now?
马克思主义者会说  那个玩偶比喻
A Marxist would say
that little parable with the toy men
对当今的金融危机
tells you everything you need
to know about the financial
作了最好的说明
crisis we've just seen.
事实上 他们会说
In fact, they'd say
你可以把过去40年的世界历史
you could explain the last 40 years
of world history
解释为资本主义不择手段
entirely in terms
of capitalism's desperate need
想要储备廉价劳动力
to have the advantages of a ready
supply of cheap labour,
但不付出成本的历史
but none of the costs.
你不必把我的话当真
And you don't have to take
my word for it.
让我们用马克思主义理论
Let's take a look at the last
40 years of history
回顾过去40年的历史
through the prism of Marxist theories.
看看他们是如何解释我们的遭遇的
To show how they might explain
the mess we're in.
想象一个马克思主义的电视台
An imaginary Marxist Broadcasting
Corporation
70年代的阶级斗争
肯定是他们眼里的好时光
would see it all as a good-old,
1970s-style class struggle.
通常 他们把世界分为工人和资本家
As usual, the world's divided
between workers and capitalists,
他们总是在为分得更多的蛋糕而争斗
always fighting to get a bigger
slice of the pie.
马克思主义者会说  危机频频爆发
And the crisis happened,
Marxists would argue,
原因是 劳资斗争中获胜的常常是资本家
because the capitalists have been
coming out on top a bit too often.
争议的焦点是工资
The fight is over wages.
资本家想压低工资 而工人想挣更多
Capitalists want to pay less -
the workers want to get more.
同意的请举手
All those in favour, please show.
70年代 强大的工会组织通过抗争
为自己赢得高工资
In the '70s, powerful trade unions
battled to keep wages high.
但到了80年代  胜利的天平倒向资方
Then we come to the '80s.
Fight back time for capitalists.
在马克思主义者看来
玛格丽特・撒切尔和罗纳德・里根
Marx would have seen
Margaret Thatcher and Ronald Regan
代表的完全是资方的利益
as acting purely in the interests
of the capitalist bosses.
他们的政府帮助资方
It was their governments
that helped business
消除任何障碍  以削减工资
by getting rid of the obstacles
that made it hard to cut wages.
恐吓跟暴力
The violence and intimidation
永远不会成功
we have seen should never have happened.
他们是激进主义者  是人民内部的敌人
It is the work of extremists.
It is the enemy within.
48小时内 如果他们还不回岗位
If they do not report for work
in 48 hours
他们就永远别回来了 等待他们的是失业
they have forfeited their jobs
and will be terminated.
发言完毕
End of statement.
对于马克思主义的电台来说
So, for the Marxist
Broadcasting Corporation,
自1980年代起  胜利的一直是资方
the capitalist won in the 1980s,
and they kept on winning.
工人们享受的高工资和就业保障
The guaranteed high wages
and job security
随着70年代一去不复返了
that workers had enjoyed
until the seventies had gone.
下行的薪资走势
And downward pressure on wages
started to lay the seeds
为今天的危机埋下了祸根
of the crisis we see today.
节目很棒  事情真是这样吗
Well, it's great telly.
Is it actually true?
马克思的历史观在一件事情上是正确的
Well, we know the Marxist view of
history is right about one thing,
至少对英国和美国是这样
at least in Britain and America.
过去几年来 处于金子塔顶的人收入激增
Earnings at the very top have
soared in the last few years
而其他人的剩余价值被榨干
and everyone else has been squeezed.
在英国 危机爆发前高速发展的十年间
In Britain, real earnings have been
flat or falling
人们的实际收入没怎么长 甚至下跌了
for the best part of ten years,
since before the crisis.
而在美国 70年代以来都是那样
And in America, that's been
happening since the '70s.
美国全职的男性工人
In the United States,
a full-time male worker,
取中位数的话
他们的平均工资30多年没变了
median income has stagnated
for a third of a century.
没有增加
No increase.
家庭收入跟15年前一样
Household income today is the same
as it was fifteen years ago.
增长的部分都被塔顶的人吸收了
All the increase to the income
has gone to the top.
在美国  1%最富有的家庭
The share of income
in the United States
他们的财富占全国财富的比率
that was going to the top 1%
of the households
20年前是12%
20 years ago, was around 12%.
如今 这个数字增加到23%
Today that share is closer to 23%.
在英国  形势还不至于那样
Things haven't gone
that far in the UK
但不平的现象在加剧
but inequality is certainly
creeping up the agenda.
是贪婪的资本家掏空了工人的钱袋吗
So, have the greedy capitalists been
picking the pockets of the workers?
为什么我说 财富都流进高层了呢
So, why do I think all that money's
been flowing to the top?
我不认为这其中有什么阴谋
Well, I don't think
it's a big conspiracy
只不过 社会和政治的变革
but there have been social
and political changes
造成了这一变化
that have made a difference.
过去 我们有强有力的工会
We used to have really big unions,
曾对富人刻以高额的税率
we used to have very high tax rates
on rich people.
还有一定的社会规范
And we had social norms.
银行家们可不能
It just wasn't done for the people
running a bank
给自己开天价的工资
to take a huge chunk of the profits
for themselves.
这些都限制了社会不平等现象的恶化
Those things helped keep
a lid on inequality.
但这些都不再有了
We don't have them anymore.
但问题最关键的还在于
But really crucial to all of this
我们的经济结构变了
has been the changing
structure of our economy.
新的科技在其中扮演了重要角色
A lot of it's down to new technology.
工作由机器取代了人手
Work previously done by hand
is now done by machines.
不再需要那么多工人了
机器能胜任任何工作
Fewer workers needed, there are more
competing for every job,
资方现在能进一步压低人工了
meaning bosses can pay them less.
也许 全球化是更重要的因素
But perhaps the most significant
factor is globalisation.
贸易壁垒进一步取消
With falling barriers
to trade around the world,
全球化使资方能获得巨大的廉价劳动力
global business has gained access to
a giant new pool of cheaper labour.
伴随着新兴市场的是
You have brought into the market now
上亿的新劳力
millions and millions of new workers.
中国 印度 以及亚洲其它国家
In China, in India,
in other parts of Asia,
还有南美的巴西等国
in parts of South America,
Brazil, for instance.
全球化的过程
So, that process has transformed
使得劳资比例被纳入到全球范围
the capital labour ratio
on a global scale.
举例来说 一位分析师可以坐在菲律宾
For example an analyst can as well
be sitting in the Philippines
或是孟买的家中工作
or in Mumbai to do the job
that is done
而同样的工作在纽约的成本就很高
at a much higher price in New York.
很多富裕国家的工人们
Many workers in the rich countries
不得不面临数以亿计的
are now competing with
an industrial reserve army
产业后备军的竞争
running into the billions.
我认为新兴市场经济体
I think, in emerging market economies,
他们会完全欢迎眼下发生的事
there'd be an overwhelming vote
in favour of what has happened
因为几乎所有人的日子都比以前好过
because almost everyone is better off
than they were,
他们早盼着这天了
and would have been.
然而很少证据表明 在发达国家
But that's less evident in the
industrialised world
低收入者的工资走低
where many lower paid people
have become even lower paid
与新兴市场国家有关  这必须得注意
relative to those who have prospered,
and that is a concern.
二战后很多年
For years after World War II
我们很肯定地认为马克思错了
we could be pretty sure
Marx was wrong.
资本主义不是很兴盛吗
Where you had capitalism,
it was working pretty well.
潮水上涨不是托起了所有的船只了吗
You could talk about
a rising tide lifting all boats,
但是 看看今天的全球经济
but you look at the global economy today
你会发现马克思眼中的资本主义
and I think you see a capitalism
that Marx would recognise.
它使中国数百万人摆脱了贫困
It's lifted hundreds of millions
out of poverty in China,
但对于西方的普通人而言
but for most ordinary people
in the West,
这套制度不再适用
the system's not working at all.
他们与资本主义的婚姻看似要破裂了
For them, capitalism's not coming
through on its side of the deal.
有分析亮起警报
It's an analysis that rings true
甚至世界最大经济体的领导者都意识到
even for the leader
of the world's biggest economy.
早在经济衰退来临前
Long before the recession,
制造业的就业机会就开始向海外转移
jobs in manufacturing began
leaving our shores.
科技令商业更高效
Technology made businesses
more efficient
但同时也淘汰了一些行业
but also made some jobs obsolete.
精英们发现他们的荷包前所未有的增长
Folks at the top saw their incomes
rise like never before.
但大多数努力工作的美国人却深受煎熬
But most hardworking Americans
struggled
开支上升  工资却没有上升
with costs that were growing,
pay cheques that weren't
债台不断高筑
and personal debt that kept piling up.
马克思会说我们现在遭受的严重的经济危机
Marx would say this squeeze on wages
was the root cause
其根源就在于资本家榨取剩余价值
of the huge economic crisis
that we've been living through.
但马克思主义者的解释有个问题
But you might see a problem
with the Marxist explanation.
如果什么都归结为低工资
If it was all down to low wages,
那你就能预期  危机将由
you'd expect the crisis
to have started
民生方面或实体经济引发
where people spend their pay,
out in the real economy.
两者必居其一
One way or another,
二战后绝大多数的衰退都是这么开始的
that is how most of the recessions
since the war have got started.
但这次 使城市沦陷的不是街头
But this time it wasn't the high
street that sank the city...
它完全来自另一个方向
it was the other way round.
2008年 引爆全球经济危机的
The explosion that rocked the global
economy in 2008
竟是银行内部
was detonated deep inside the banks.
那么 马克思是怎么把低工资
跟劣质银行联系在一起的呢
So, how would Marx link low wages
to troubled banks?
答案是 他视资本具有极强的适应能力
The answer is - he saw
capital as endlessly adaptable.
它解决低薪资问题的同时
It could solve one problem -
low wages...
又创造出新的问题
but only at the cost
of creating another.
记住 马克思从未低估过资本主义
Remember, Marx didn't
underestimate capitalism.
他只是认为它有天生的缺陷
He thought it was
fundamentally flawed.
并没有说资本主义是愚笨的
He didn't think it was stupid.
如果大多数人的收入不足以
If large parts of the population
weren't being paid enough
满足他们的需求
马克思绝不会惊叹于
to support demand, well, he wouldn't
have been at all surprised
资本主义又一项闪亮的发明
to hear that capitalists had come up
with a brilliant solution,
信用卡
the credit card.
你确定都带齐了吗 钱呢
Now are you sure you've got
everything, Money?
我看看  酒 ...
Let me see, wine...
有了消费信贷 即便没钱
With consumer credit, people can
carry on spending,
人们都可以继续消费
even if they haven't got the money.
经济情况良好 资本家仍有利可图
The economy stays afloat, and the
capitalists still make their profit.
信用卡对于资本主义的顽疾倒是一剂良方
So, credit provided an answer
to all of capitalism's woes.
但这只能持续一段时间
But only for a while.
记得不 马克思认为资本主义制度
有其先天的缺陷
Remember, Marx thought the system
was fundamentally flawed.
资本家也许都很聪明
They might be very clever,
these capitalists,
但现在 他们比以往任何时候
都苟延残喘
but now, more than ever,
they were living on borrowed time.
其实 这不仅仅是信用卡的问题
As we know,
it went well beyond credit cards.
危机爆发的根本原因
What ultimately brought the crisis
to a head
是巨额的抵押贷款
was the billions borrowed on mortgages.
人们以为他们的物业将一直升值
People thought the value of their
house would keep going up for ever.
住房抵押贷款这事很妙
Housing credit is beautiful
因为如果房价一直上涨
because if your house price is increasing
依靠房子的升值作抵押贷款
and you're borrowing against the
increase in value of your house,
你都不会感到是在举债
you don't feel you're borrowing
your way into debt.
但其实 你是在举债
But, of course, you are.
房贷现象在美国大规模上演
In America,it happened on a massive scale.
那儿 资产阶级越来越富有
There, as we know, the capitalists
were getting richer and richer.
有点闲钱 他们不会都用来消费
They couldn't spend
all of their extra money.
一如往常 在逐利本性的驱使下
Driven, as ever, by the desire
to make more profit,
他们把钱投入到风险越来越大的项目中
they lent it out in riskier
and riskier ways.
这种贷款方式的名字您也许不陌生
The name given to this lending might
well be familiar.
次级房贷
Subprime.
美国发生的实际上是
What we did is, as the incomes
当大多数美国人的收入停滞
of most Americans were stagnating,
甚至下跌
or even declining,
有人却说：“别为这担心
we said, "Don't let it bother you.
继续消费  就当收入在涨”
"Keep spending
as if your income was going up."
这套还真管用
And they did that very well.
谁会反对呢  银行还在挣钱
I mean, who would oppose it?
The banks who are making money?
业主也买到了房子
The households
who are getting their house?
政客把选民哄得爽歪歪
The politicians who have happy
constituents?
没有一个人
I mean, there is nobody
整个过程没人不爽  直到最后崩盘
who's going to be unhappy
in this process until it collapses.
最后怎么收场的我们都明白
And we all know how it ended.
现在回想起来 问题很清楚
In retrospect, it seems obvious.
借贷给没有偿还能力的人
Lending to people
who couldn't afford it
这怎么可能永久地解决问题呢
wasn't a lasting solution to anything.
最终房地产泡沫破裂
It led to a housing bubble which burst,
危及一些世界级大银行
threatening some of the world's
biggest banks,
拜全球经济一体化之赐
and thanks to our integrated world,
肇始于美国的危机
what started in the United States
波及整个经济体
spread and infected the entire system,
全球经济随之衰退
causing a global recession.
这就是马克思主义者对危机的解释
So, here's the Marxist explanation
for the crisis we've just seen.
经济的全球化
You've got a global economy
使商业越做越大
with businesses
getting better and better
薪资压低产生出更多利润
at squeezing wages
and pushing up profits.
但有一个问题
But there's a problem.
生产过剩
They're producing a lot of stuff
但工人无力购买
that the workers can no longer afford,
而热钱还在追逐新的投资方向
and a lot of profits looking for a new home.
于是 全球的房产泡沫成为新的方向
A global property bubble provided
an answer to both those problems.
整个系统继续运行 但债务堆积如山
The system was kept afloat
on a mountain of debt
它的崩塌只是时间问题
but it was only a matter of time
before it all came crashing down.
资本主义当时貌似强大 但那只是暂时的
Capitalism's only ever as strong
as its latest, temporary fix.
这听起来像离奇的传说 很多人会说
It's an extraordinary tale
and a lot of people would say
这完全是一派胡言
it's completely wrong.
马克思主义说的不对
Marxism doesn't actually work,
它不过就是哗众取宠 能不时吸引人罢了
but it keeps coming back,
cos it makes for a good story.
我不认为危机跟低工资有什么关系
I don't think low wages played any
role at all in causing the crisis.
危机的根源在政府和中央银行
The crisis was caused by governments
and central banks
向市场注入了太多低息贷款
flooding the market with cheap credit
and cheap money
因为政客们不想看到经济出现拐点
because politicians don't like the
downturn in an economy
那会加大失业人口
that throws people out of work.
我认为从某种意义上说
I think it may have,to some degree,
政府增加了负债额
increased the level of indebtedness
不仅使人们陷入危机
that people went into the crisis with,
更使危机加剧
which, I think, intensifies
how deep the crisis became,
但这还不是根本的原因
but it wasn't the underlying cause.
是整个大环境使情况更为恶化
It was a contextual factor
which made it a bit worse.
即便马克思的思想一直都被认为是有害的
但其低工资促成危机的理论
But the idea that low wages
may have contributed to the crisis
越来越被人所接受
is gaining ground, even if the name
Marx is as toxic as ever.
乔治・马格纳斯是全球顶级银行的
George Magnus
is a senior economic adviser
资深经济顾问
to one of the world's leading banks.
危机爆发后 您写了很多有关马克思的文章
You've been writing quite a lot
about Marx since this crisis started.
您怎么重新评价他的呢
How did you come to look at him again?
实际上 从这个交易所就能理解
Actually it was on this trading floor.
雷曼倒下前的一个周末
It was probably the weekend
before Lehman's went bust,
这个地方通常有些喧闹
and it's normally a little bit noisy,
但那时
but at the time it was...
这里安静地连掉根针都能听见
you could hear a pin drop,
it was that deathly quiet
我感觉全球金融体系都快崩溃了
and I could almost feel, you know,
that the global system was frozen.
真是惊恐万分
And it was quite a scary thought.
这使我又重新回顾了
It took me back to a lot of the
things that I used to read about
我年轻时曾经看过的很多东西
and study when I was much younger...
那会儿 读马克思完全是为了好玩
the days when I actually read Marx for fun.
你还写了文章 发表后有什么反响
And you wrote about that,
and what was the reaction?
我得说 我收到了很多恐吓信
I did get a lot of hate mail,
I have to say.
很多人对社会主义 马克思主义
There are a lot of people
who were quite opposed to the idea
的思想非常反感
that anything that was
socialistic or Marxist,
主流们对之很警惕
you know, could be at all considered
serious in the mainstream.
很多恐吓信件来自美国
A lot of this hate mail, I have to
say, came from the United States
我被人责骂为奥巴马的傀儡
and I was accused of being, you know,
an Obama clone and...
总统奥巴马  大家熟知的马克思主义者
是的 大家熟知的马克思主义者
President Obama - the well-known
Marxist. The well-known Marxist!
真是不可思议
Very mysterious forces.
有很多反对之声来自
So, there was a lot of negative
reaction from, I think
你能预计到的那些
people that probably
predictably, you know,
意识形态固化的人
had already tied their own
ideological colours to the mast.
发现马克思的真知灼见
But the people who do find value
in Marx
并不意味着就是马克思主义者
aren't necessarily going
to follow him all the way.
我认为 马克思有助于我们廓清问题
I think Marx helps
in framing the problem,
但考虑到我们身处不同的环境
but I think the solutions
have to be different,
解决之道真的很难
given the different environment
we are in.
但有一点除外 马克思坚称
资本主义的陷落不可避免
Except, Marx would insist,
the trap is inescapable.
资本家必须全力追逐利润
Capitalists must seek profit
above all else
否则他们就会破产
or they'll go out of business.
所以 他们凭什么会
So, why would they ever choose
让渡给工人更多份额呢
to give workers a bigger share of
the pie?
马克思说 我们得走出危机
What Marx would say is that we have
to look for ways out of this crisis,
但那得放眼远方
which look beyond the restoration
资产阶级是不能指望的
of capitalist class power.
我想 此时正是我们重新思考
And, I think, this is a time when
we actually need to start thinking
革命性的解决方案的时候了
about the revolutionary
solution again.
但说到造反 谁造谁的反呢
But who, exactly,
is revolting against who?
马克思把世界分为工人和资本家
Marx divided the world
neatly into workers and capitalists
但今天看来 这一僵硬的划分
变得模糊不清
but today his stark distinction
is incredibly blurred.
老板们也在为自己工作
工人们也分得他们的份额
Bosses work for themselves
and workers own shares.
现代社会下
大多数人的利益与社会休戚相关
In our modern world, enough of us do
have a stake in the system,
移动电话也好 退休计划也罢
whether mobile phones
or pension plans,
没人想要革命
to stave off talk of armed revolt.
但资本主义下失意的人怎么办
But what about the people
capitalism's failing?
马克思怎么关照这些人呢
What does Marx have to say to them?
马克思对现代社会有深刻的洞见
这着实令人惊讶
It's really amazing how well Marx
seems to understand our world,
我们比任何时候都与他人紧密相连
where we're more interconnected
than he could ever have imagined
资本主义的各个方面  好与坏
and where all the faces
of capitalism, good and bad,
都呈现于世界任何角落
are now on display in pretty much
every corner of the globe.
但马克思说过一句著名的话
But he was the one who famously said
重要的不是解释这个世界
而是改变这个世界
it wasn't enough to interpret the
world - the point was to change it.
如果你问他 我们该做什么来取代资本主义
If you ask him what exactly we're
supposed to replace capitalism with,
那他很可能无言以对
well, he had remarkably little
to say about that.
在其晚年
As Marx entered his final years,
马克思似乎对一切都安然接受
he seemed quite content
with the way things were.
他穷了一辈子
He'd been poor
for a lot of his life,
但到1865年 他已有足够的钱移居伦敦市郊
but by 1856, he had enough money
to move to London's suburbs.
年轻的叛乱分子
如今看来就像是体制内人士
The young firebrand now looked
like part of the establishment.
他会在汉普特斯西斯公园漫步
He would spend his day
walking around Hampstead Heath
担忧自己的理财状况
and he would worry about personal finances,
还有他的女儿们
he would worry about his daughters
钢琴课的花销
and the expense of their piano lessons.
从很多方面看 他过的就是资产阶级的生活
I mean, he lived a remarkably
bourgeois life, in many ways.
后来 马克思成为世界革命的权威
In his later years, Marx was the
world authority on the revolution,
但他本人似乎并不急于看到革命的发生
but he didn't seem to be in a hurry
to make it happen.
来自世界各地 年轻的
头脑发热的社会主义者
Young hot-headed socialists
from around the world
慕名来到北伦敦 希望获得他的支持
would come to North London to pay
their respects, win his support.
马克思高兴的等待他们的到来
Mr M seemed happy to watch and wait.
马克思完全鄙视恐怖主义
Marx only really had contempt
for terrorists,
反对激进的政治运动
those who were seeking
to fast-forward political progress
反对专横的暴力革命
by having change
through arbitrary violence.
要紧的是改革经济基础
You needed the economic fundamentals
in place
那才是正确的革命方式
for a proper revolution to succeed.
要理解为什么马克思不想要冒进的革命
To understand why he didn't want
to rush revolution
我们必须更深入地了解马克思主义的理论
we need to understand -
for the last time, I promise...
这也是我最后要提请大家注意的
a bit more Marxist theory.
一如往常
马克思对世界史做了宏大的分析
As usual, he had a grand analysis
of the history of the world.
他洞见到 人类历经穴居时代
He saw the great
sweep of humanity's endeavours,
希腊罗马时期的奴隶社会
from the caveman,
以及之后诸侯割据的封建社会
to the slave societies
of Greece and Rome,
这都是人类自身的巨大飞跃
to the feudalism
of kings and castles.
此后 基于劳资关系的资本主义社会
All of which was replaced, in turn,
by our own capitalist system
取而代之
of bosses and workers.
这一制度绝对不公平
Incredibly unfair,
但生产力也绝对惊人
but also incredibly productive.
马克思说  只有资本主义
Marx said only when we'd got
everything we could
不再能给予我们所需的时候
out of capitalism
我们才会发动革命
could we afford to have a revolution.
用他的话说就是
“资本主义私有制的丧钟就要响了
In his words, "the knell of
capitalist private property sounds,
剥夺者就要被剥夺了。”
"the expropriators are expropriated,
资本主义的一切
"all to be replaced by
都将被取代
"more or less nothing."
但令人烦恼的是 他并没有指明方向
Irritatingly there's next to no
alternative laid out.
总的来说 马克思
Marx, basically,
没有给我们设计什么蓝图
was not the one who simply gave us a
blueprint, you know,
资本主义完了后 怎么个五步曲啦
five stages after capitalism...
共产主义的基本方针啦
communism, here you have the basic
guidelines,
行动指南啦 等等
what to do, and so on.
这些他都没说   完全留给了我们
No, no, it's up to us.
他只是向我们打开了一扇窗
He just opened up the field.
资本主义之外 还有什么体制吗
Is there an alternative to capitalism?
我不知道
I've no idea.
也许会有很多替代方案
Well, I suppose there could be all
kinds of alternatives.
死寂  挨饿
Dead silence, starvation,
或世界毁灭
or the end of the world or anything,
但我是压根想不到还有什么出路
but I simply have no idea
if there is an alternative.
我觉得这并不重要
It doesn't occur to me, it doesn't
seem to me to be important.
这就好比说  天气有得换吗
It's like saying,
is there an alternative to weather?
马克思说  我们无法预测
Marx said we couldn't describe
what the next stage of human
development
人类发展的下个阶段是什么  就好比
would look anymore than
a feudal serf
一个农奴无法理解我们现代的生活一样
could have described
our lives today,
对此 你或许会说“很公平嘛”
to which you might say,
"fair enough."
除非你只把这当作是句俏皮话
Except you might also think
it was pretty telling.
毕竟 没人能给出一个
After all, nobody else
has been able to describe
令人信服的资本主义的替代方案
a convincing alternative
to capitalism either.
我想 如果马克思能再多活10年
I think he would have
written a lot more
他会更多着墨于
had he lived ten years more,
社会主义的共和制这一主题
on what a socialist republic
would look like,
没准这真的能给世界带来安宁
谁又说得准呢
and who knows, but that might have
saved the world a lot of bother.
没有他的蓝图
接下来发生了什么我们都看到了
Without his blueprint,
we all know what happened next.
与马克思预期相反 在富有的发达国家
There weren't any revolutions
没有爆发革命
in the rich, developed countries,
as Marx predicted.
相反 革命爆发在某个最穷的国家
Instead it happened in one
of the world's poorest nations.
苏俄也许跟马克思想象的共产主义相距甚远
Soviet Russia may have left Marx
far behind
但这确是一次尝试
but it was an attempt
to try something else,
从它的失败中 我们获益良多
and many have drawn lessons
from its failure.
事实上  资本主义各式各样
The truth is, at the moment there
are different forms of capitalism.
但若谈及 你是想要
But on the big argument
about whether you really want
资本主义还是共产主义这一大问题时
to have a communist system
or a capitalist one,
我想 回答几乎是一定的
that is pretty much won everywhere
I think.
资本主义有人性的
There are more humane versions
of capitalism
也有残酷的
or more barbaric forms of capitalism.
但要说完全取代它  我不看好
But I don't think there's a systemic
alternative to capitalism.
未来有可能吗？  我想会吧
Will there ever be?
Yes, I would think so.
没什么是永恒的嘛
I mean, you know, nothing is for ever.
绝对没有 资本主义也不例外
Absolutely nothing,
and capitalism is not for ever.
但任何人若要寻求一个更公平的制度
But anyone looking
for a fairer alternative
千万不能忘记柏林墙以东发生的事
knows they can't ever repeat what
happened east of the Berlin Wall.
独裁 政治压迫 数百万生命被践踏
Dictatorship, political oppression
and millions of ruined lives.
1945到1989年
From 1945 till 1989,
这里是共产主义东德的重要监狱
this was the main remand centre
for political prisoners
羁押的都是政治犯
in communist East Germany.
如今 这里已是一座纪念馆
Today it's been turned into a memorial.
这儿奉行一个特别的理念
There was a special ideology.
逮捕即有罪
Whoever we arrest,he or she is guilty.
类似这样的地方或许解释了
It's possible that places like this
为什么今日对资本主义
即便批评再怎么严厉
explain why even capitalism's
toughest critics today
但几乎很少有人提出要取而代之
seldom talk seriously
about replacing it.
在欧洲的希腊等国到处是抗议之声
You can see with all these protests
in Europe, Greece, and so on.
我曾在西班牙 希腊问人们相同的问题
I was in Spain, in Greece,
asking always the same question,
那好 你们究竟要什么呢
OK, what do you want?
除了一些纯粹诉诸道德的答案外
Apart from some purely
moralistic answers,
没啥有益 建设性的答案
I didn't get any good,
complete proposals,
回答都类似
you know, answers like,
"是钱为人服务 而不是人为钱服务"
"Oh, money should serve people,
not people serving money."
上帝啊 我肯定
连希特勒都会同意这套说辞
My God, Hitler and everyone would
have agreed with this, I'm sure.
您也许会认为
You would have thought that with this
implosion of the banking system
随着英美以及其它国家
at the heart of capitalism
in the United States
居于资本主义核心地位的银行的崩盘
as well as the United Kingdom,
and so on,
会有一股强大的势头
there would be a huge rush
倒向马克思主义和激进的社会主义
to Marxism and extreme socialism.
但那没有发生
That hasn't really happened.
这很让人惊讶  对此我很欣慰
It is quite surprising
and I'm very pleased.
但如果人们对这样的地方记忆慢慢消退
But if memories
of this place do fade,
是否又会想着给资本主义找替代方案呢
could there ever be
an alternative to capitalism,
亦或者这个地方应该成为人们永恒的记忆呢
or should what happened here be
a lesson for all time?
有人想寻求资本主义的替代方案
If someone wants to seek
an alternative to capitalism,
并声称通过努力
and they're saying
by seeking that alternative
能超越资本主义
that capitalism is a system
rather than a fact of life,
他们或许还会说
and they're saying that,for instance,
人性可以改变
that human nature can be altered,
但这根本就是乌托邦
fundamentally they're revealing
themselves as utopian.
而乌托邦的最大问题是
And the problem with utopia
血海深渊是它唯一的路径
is that it can only ever be
approached across a sea of blood
而且它永远也实现不了
and you never arrive.
说左翼人士是乌托邦 这是对我们的大不敬
This is my big mantra, when we
leftists are accused of utopians.
或许吧   但真正的乌托邦是
Maybe, but the only real utopia
is to think
面对现实 只作小修小补
that with some cosmetic changes
真正的变革遥遥无期
things can go on indefinitely
the way they are now.
起来 斯大林主义者们
Arise ye Stalins from your slumbers
起来 全世界受苦的人
Arise ye criminals of want
满腔的热血已经沸腾
For reason in revolt now thunders
要为真理而斗争
And at last ends the age of can't. ?
马克思卒于1883年
Marx died in 1883.
在他墓前 马克思一生的挚友和同志
In a speech at his grave, his long
time friend and collaborator,
弗里德里希・恩格斯称
Freidrich Engels,
他的英名功绩将被时代所铭记
declared his name and work will
endure through the ages.
他的名字的确深深地烙印于
20世纪大部分时间
For most of the 20th century
his name did endure,
但很多是对他的误解
though, usually,
for all the wrong reasons.
如今 21世纪
But now it's 21st century,
这位过世已久的普鲁士人
会留给我们怎样的忠告呢
what can this long-dead Prussian
really say to us?
我认为 最主要的是 马克思提醒我们
Fundamentally,
I think Marx reminds us
如果资本主义不是为所有人服务
那它就没有生命力
that if capitalism doesn't work for
everyone, it might not work at all.
面对目前发生的事
以及薪资方面的危机
When you look at what's happening
and the pressure on wages,
你怎么理解 有人
can you understand why people are
sort of looking again
如此怀念马克思主义呢
at some of Marx's analysis?
是的  这是个热点
Yes, it... The big picture.
劳资关系
The workers versus the capitalists.
毫无疑问
在社会不平等 及收入分配方面
And there is no doubt that there
have been significant changes
有显著的变化
in inequality and in the
distribution of income,
这使我们对已有的成功和财富
which make you pause about
the benefits of the developments
有了一丝疑虑
of output and prosperity
that we've seen.
但我认为 你不能想当然
And I don't think you can afford
以为市场经济的优势
to believe that the benefits
of a market economy
――它给我们带来财富会一直持续
in bringing prosperity
will be there
除非人们有共同的诉求
这套制度才能良好运转
unless there is a collective
commitment to keep the system going,
这就需要人们秉持
and that does require people to believe
人人受益的原则
that everyone will benefit in the end.
我认为 资本主义某些丑陋的一面
I think some of the ugliness
of capitalism
如马克思在19世纪看到的那些
that he saw in the 19th century
似乎在20 21世纪重演了
seems to be appearing
in the 20th and 21st,
我们必须提请这方面的关注
and in a way we have to keep
our perspective on this.
人们的健康是比以前好了
The health conditions are much better,
生活条件也更好了
living standards are starting
from a higher level,
但问题是
but it is still the case that
情况离理想状态还很远
things aren't the way they ought to be.
并没有朝正确的方向迈进
And they're not moving
in the way they should be.
让我们面对现实
马克思并不只是个补锅匠
But let's face it, Marx wasn't just
talking about tweaking the system.
他有更远大的抱负
He had a much grander claim
than that.
马克思改变了世界吗
那当然
Did Marx change the world?
Of course he did.
在他葬礼过后
And after that funeral,
然们在他的墓前撒下热泪
people did weep hot tears
at his grave,
正如17岁的他曾梦想见到的那样
just as his 17-year-old self
would have wanted.
也许有更多人想诅咒他
Probably many more
lived to curse his name.
但无可置疑的是 资本主义还在
But there's no getting round it,
capitalism's still here.
马克思正确地洞察到资本主义
与生俱来的不稳定性
Marx was right to see capitalism
as inherently unstable
以及经常的不公平现象
and often unfair.
凯恩斯和哈耶克也看到了这点
但马克思走的最远
Keynes and Hayek saw that too,
but Marx was the first
不同于这两位大师
他认为我们应抛弃资本主义制度
and unlike them, he didn't think we
should find a way to live with it.
他说 危机过后
He said capitalism would
bounce back from crises
资本主义会卷土重来
and reinvent itself,
但最终 一个无法抗拒的制度
会取而代之
but in the end a compelling
alternative would appear,
资本主义制度会完全毁灭
and capitalism would collapse.
这套曾经被认为大错特错的观点
For all that rings true now in Marx,
如今听上去像是真的
on that he seems to have been
dead wrong.
没准马克思真的低估了资本主义
Maybe he did underestimate capitalism.
就像他高估了资本主义的对立面一样
He certainly overestimated
the opposition to it.
但我认为 资本主义真的要重铸自己
I think the system needs
to reinvent itself now, again.
若它真的能走出泥淖
If it can pull that off,
下个世纪 我们或许能忽略一下马克思
we'll be talking even less about
Marx a century from now.
但过去几年的危机
资本主义真得付出良多来为自身证明了
But the last few years have left
capitalism with plenty to prove.
公开大学制作了六部1分钟的动画片
The open University's produced six
one minute animations
介绍与我们息息相关的一些基本的经济常识
to explain some of the key economic
ideas that affect all of us,
如果您想了解什么是“看不见的手”
so, if you want to spot
an invisible hand,
或其它经济学奥妙
or other secrets of economics,
请访问：
go to...
其中有公开大学的网址
and follow the link
to the Open University.
英文字幕提供： MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.
====================
纪录片之家倾情奉献
http://www.jlpzj.net/
中字翻译：小开心  校对：hello @纪录片之家
本字幕仅供学习交流 严禁用于商业用途
==================================